<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A discourse more at large of the late ouerthrovve giuen to the King of Spaines armie at Turnehaut, in Ianuarie last, by Count Morris of Nassawe, assisted with the English forces whereunto is adioined certaine inchauntments and praiers in Latine, found about diuerse of the Spaniards, which were slaine in the same conflict: Translated out of French according to the copy printed in the Low Countries. Seene and allowed.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1597</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 26 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A12676</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 22993</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S101965</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99837768</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99837768</idno>
            <idno type="VID">2110</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A12676)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2110)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1035:09)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A discourse more at large of the late ouerthrovve giuen to the King of Spaines armie at Turnehaut, in Ianuarie last, by Count Morris of Nassawe, assisted with the English forces whereunto is adioined certaine inchauntments and praiers in Latine, found about diuerse of the Spaniards, which were slaine in the same conflict: Translated out of French according to the copy printed in the Low Countries. Seene and allowed.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 4 [i.e. 14] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[By P[eter] Short] are to be sold [by J. Flasket and P. Linley] in Paules Churchyarde, at the signe of the black Beare,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1597.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's and publishers' names from STC.</note>
                  <note>Page 14, final page, misnumbered 4.</note>
                  <note>With engraved frontispiece bound before leaf A1.</note>
                  <note>A translation of the French original.</note>
                  <note>Caption title reads: A discourse of the victorie which it pleased God to giue vnto the Prince of Nassawe, captaine generall of the vnited Prouinces of the Low countries, in the ouerthrowe of the armie of the king of Spaine, at Turnhaut in Brabant, the 24. of Ianuarie last.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Netherlands --  History --  Wars of Independence, 1556-1648 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Turnhout, Battle of, 1547 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:2110:1"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>portrait of Maurice of Nassau, Prince of Orange</figDesc>
                  <head>MAVRITIUS PRINCEPS ORANGIAE COMES NASSAVIAE. ETC.</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:2110:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A diſcourſe more at large of the late ouerthrovve giuen to the King of Spaines armie at <hi>Turnehaut, in Ianuarie laſt, by Count</hi> Morris of Naſſawe, aſſiſted with the Engliſh forces:</p>
            <p>Wh<gap reason="illegible" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>o is adioined certaine inchauntments <hi>and praiers in Latine, found about diuerſe of the Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards,</hi> which were ſlaine in the ſame conflict:</p>
            <p>Tranſlated out of French according to the copy printed in the Low Cou<gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ies, <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>and allowed.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <head>P S</head>
               <q xml:lang="lat">ET V<gap reason="illegible" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>D N<gap reason="illegible" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> V<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>RI<gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> TVA</q>
               <figDesc>printer's device, consisting of an open book surrounded by beams of light and motto "Et usque ad nubes veritas tua," with the initials of the printer Peter Short (1589-1603) below</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>Printed at London, and are to be ſolde in Paules Churchyarde, at the ſigne of the blacke Beare. 1597.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="newsbook">
            <pb facs="tcp:2110:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:2110:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A diſcourſe of the victorie which it pleaſed God to giue vnto the Prince of <hi>Naſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſaw,</hi> captaine generall of the vnited Prouin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the Low countries, in the ouerthrowe of the Armie of the king of Spaine, at <hi>Turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haut</hi> in <hi>Brabant,</hi> the 24. of Ianuarie laſt.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q xml:lang="lat">Tandem bona cauſa Triumphant.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F the euents of the affairs of the worlde did ſucceede according to the iudgementes and reaſon of men, it would fal out by an infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible maxime, of that which we call the order &amp; reaſon of things, that the ſmalleſt ſhoulde bee ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounted of the greateſt, the moſt ſimpleſt, poore and meekeſt, by the moſt craftieſt, ſub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tileſt and richeſt, and the weakeſt by the ſtrongeſt. But when wee ſee the contrary to happen, that the ſmalleſt or pooreſt, the moſte ſimple and weakeſt to ouercome the greateſt, the moſt ſubtill, richeſt, and moſt mightieſt, it is an euident ſigne whereby the Atheiſts &amp; contemners of the prouidence of God, may acknowledge the actions of men to be gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by a higher power, then their weake diſcourſes can reach vnto: and likewiſe to Princes which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe themſelues to bee Chriſtians, an aduertiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment not to grounde themſelues vppon their owne greatnes and worldly wiſedome, but narrowlie to examine themſelues, whether the foundation of
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:2110:3"/> their warres be iuſt, holy, neceſſarie, and void of all tyrannical paſſions, not oppoſing themſelues obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately without yeelding to any thinge, vnder hope that their great extraordinary meanes will bringe vnder thoſe, who by compariſon haue not the hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth part in reſpect of themſelues. But that great God which doth ſuſtain thoſe whoſe cauſes are iuſt, how weake ſoeuer they be, knoweth well how to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſe their hauty preſumptions and enuie, in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king their determinations vaine and to conſume like ſmoke, whereof we might alledge infinite ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of times paſt, if one which is preſented vnto vs in this age would not ſuffice. Wee ſee the Spaniſh Nation ſo puffed vp with ambition, and ouerwhelmed with deſire of conquering almoſte all the world, for the great treaſures which yearlie hee draweth to himſelfe, that not finding any thing im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible, he doth vndertake at once to conquer three or foure Realmes, by waie of armes, beſides this heauy warre which he hath againſt the vnited pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinces of the Low countries. And albeit that theſe Spaniards in this purſute of conqueſt, haue vnpro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fitablie conſumed in two of their principal enterpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, as much treaſure, and receiued as muche dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage as euer did any prince that rained theſe thou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſand yeares in Chriſtendome: yet notwithſtanding as in deſpite of their mines of golde, they continue to force themſelues againe to ſtrike on the rockes which haue cauſed their ſhipwracke.</p>
            <p>Is it to be founde in any hiſtorie whatſoeuer theſe thouſand yeares, that one prince in one onlie exploite or enterpriſe, hath employed ſo many mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions of golde as the king of Spaine hath doone in France a few yeares ſince, during thoſe follies of
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:2110:3"/> the league, for to catch or rather diſmember that goodly realme, one of the ornaments not of <hi>Europe</hi> but of the worlde? In all the ſtreetes of the legued townes, euery tenth man did ſcarſe receaue wages of the Spaniard, and at euery receit thereof were two or three mutinies at the leaſte. As for that proude and extraordinarie armie by Sea prepared the yeare eightie eight, and ſet foorth with ſo great charges, was there euer the like by any Chriſtian prince theſe thouſand yeares? Notwithſtanding al that, the king of Spaine as I ſay more obſtinate then euer or rather entering into a reproued courſe of iudgement) doth he not yet prepare another the like? Wherof howbeit that he hath already loſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt the one halfe, yet doth he repaire it without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſparing of charges, for to ariue at a place where it ſhalbe I aſſure my ſelfe better receiued then wel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>come. He doth leuie great &amp; extraordinarie forces for this next ſummer, to the end to ouerthrow &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy all Fraunce. Fraunce I ſay, which is at this preſent ſo defenſible an eſtate, as it was at that time when as the Emperour <hi>Charles</hi> the fift his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther imploying all his forces for to make a breach in it, and thoſe of an hoſt of the princes of Germany was conſtrained to returne as ſhamefullie as hee did enter couragiouſlie, and with hope to ſwallow vp the goodlie eſtate of France I ſay againe, which is at this preſent commaunded by a king ſo braue, worthie, warlike and wiſe as euer it hath hadde, vnder colour that his armies beeing conducted the laſt ſummer paſt by his nephewe and brother in lawe the Cardinall of <hi>Auſtria</hi> haue hadde ſome fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uourable ſucceſſes by the taking of two Townes
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:2110:4" rendition="simple:additions"/> in France, and one on this ſide, the which notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding hee hath bought deerely and with his iuſte valour, and giuen money inoughe for either of them: and yet is the cardinal puffed vp with ſo high imaginations, and filled him with ſo great deſſeins, that eſteeming the Frenchmen as people made of ſtrawe or ſnowe, and as they ſay, not vnderſtanding the affaires of eſtate, do caſt as they thinke duſt in their eies, by the meanes of trifling propoſitions of peace or truce, thinking this next ſummer, to enter far into their realme, and ſo to make a breach into the vnited Prouinces. But that God (as I ſaid at the beginning) which can ouerthrow the paradox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es of their tyrannical and arrogant powers, hath alreadie made it appeere by a notable euent in this beginning of the yeare, that their determinations take not ſuche effect as they beare themſelues in hand, for that his beſt regiments of men of armes haue bin cleane ouerthrowne and cut in peeces by the Prince <hi>Maurice of Naſſau,</hi> which had atchiued ſuch aduenturous deeds of war to the good ſucceſſe of the Cardinall, and of the earle of <hi>Fueintes,</hi> and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt others, thoſe <hi>Rodomons</hi> ſoldats, <hi>Neapolitans</hi> of the regiment of the marques of <hi>Treuicques</hi> and of <hi>Borlot,</hi> which are ſaid to tear armed men with their teeth. This victorie then, is as happy, honourable, and profitable for vs, as it befell vnto them ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and domageable the 24. of this moneth of Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuarie 1597. in the Prouince of <hi>Brabant</hi> at <hi>Turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haut,</hi> in maner as followeth:</p>
            <p>The Cardinall during the ſeaſon of Winter, did thinke that he might being fauoured by the yce and froſt, attempt ſome notable thing in the partes of <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Zeland,</hi> reſolued with himſelfe to ſende
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:2110:4"/> vnto the ſaid <hi>Turnhaut</hi> a good troope of his beſt foote and horſſe, commanded by the earle of <hi>Varas,</hi> hereto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore named the Baron of <hi>Balanchon,</hi> great maiſter of the K. of Spains ordinance, &amp; brother to the mar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ques of <hi>Waranbon,</hi> inſomuch that beeing at <hi>Turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hout,</hi> he beheld thoſe Iles on the right and left hand where his determination was, the which hee iud<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ged of ſuche importance for their affaires, that in ſome of their townes they vſed great ſolemnitie in their churches, and very triumphant proceſſions, to the end that it would pleaſe God ſpeedily to ſend great froſts. But God did diſpoſe otherwiſe of the matter: for the Prince <hi>Maurice</hi> ful of valour and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtrie, and one likewiſe that letteth not paſſe anie opportunitie when it repreſenteth it ſelfe, hauing intelligence of the aſſembly of theſe forces, and that it was to g<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ue him a checke vpon the yce, reſolued with himſelfe to force them to defende themſelues who furiouſlye prepared to aſſaile him, and to this effect, he cauſed to come ſecretly with good order to a place named a <hi>rendez-vous,</hi> ſome thouſand horſe, and fiue thouſand foot, with certaine peeces of Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance, to vſe as occaſion ſhoulde ſerue, and as hee had foreſeen, and ſo marched towarde <hi>Turnehout</hi> in good order and reſolution the 24. lodging himſelfe at <hi>Rauels</hi> halfe a mile from the enimy, who wer great<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly aſtoniſhed, vnderſtanding the prince to be vppon ſuch a ſodain come ſo neer them: being thus perplex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed and vncertain, they reſolued for the beſt, to make their retrait towards <hi>Herentals,</hi> the neereſt walled town to them held by the Spaniard, beginning at four of the clocke in the morning to march forward with their baggage, and then with their menne of armes. His ex. at the very ſame inſtant, marched to<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wards <hi>Turnhout</hi> to ſet vpon the enemy, and founde
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:2110:5"/> him remooued, but yet not far from thence, which made him to reſolue to purſue the enimy, &amp; to fighte with him in plaine field: and for to begin the order, two C. Engliſh Muſquetiers did aduance them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, to the end that they holding continuall ſkir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh with the enimy, he might not ſo eaſily proceede on his way, and in the meanewhile the reſt of his company had opportunity to ioine with him, for co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming out of the towne, the way was very bad and ful of water: then he aduanced his horſſemen, which kept themſelues ſtil coaſting the enemye, whoe not long after was diſcried to approch toward the end of that great plaine and ready to enter into a ſtrait both narrow and trobleſome, where the horſe loſte their aduantage and the foot did win it: then was it reſolued, that his Ex. ſhould no longer delaie but to come to the matter: howbeit the greateſt parte of the footmen were farre behinde. This thus re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolued, the charge was giuen in this order.</p>
            <p>The earle of <hi>Hoenloo</hi> his brother in law, a braue and reſolute nobleman, accompanied with the earle of <hi>Solms,</hi> charged the enemy in the forefront, wher was a regiment of <hi>Almaines</hi> of xiii. companies making the vangard: ſir <hi>Robert Sidney</hi> gouernour of Fluſhing, and ſir <hi>Frances Vere</hi> Collonel of an engliſh regiment, a knight both valiant and wiſe, whoe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides their intertaining of the enimy in ſkirmiſh; ſet vpon the rereward where the <hi>Neapolitans</hi> were: o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther troopes were commanded to charge the flank, where were the regiments of the L. of <hi>Hachicourt,</hi> which wer hertofore thoſe of <hi>Mounſieur de la Motre,</hi> compounded of olde ſouldiors, and thoſe of the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonel <hi>a Barlotte,</hi> and almoſt all at one inſtant. The cauallery of the enimy iſſued with fiue of their beſt cornets: to wit, three of Spaniards, of <hi>Don Iuan de
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:2110:5" rendition="simple:additions"/> Cordua, Don Iuan de Gouzman, &amp; Don alonce de Mon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dragon,</hi> one <hi>Albanoice du S. Nicolas Baſte,</hi> one of the oldeſt and ſufficienteſt captaines, and the other of the Low countries of the L. of <hi>Grobendonc,</hi> ſeeing our men come to charge them, they beganne to flie without any other fight, forſaking their companio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s on foot, the which after very little reſiſtance by the meanes of ours were broken and ouerthrowne: his Ex. being accompanied with the L. Admiral of <hi>Naſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſau</hi> and Collonel <hi>Moray</hi> were reſerued to ſuſtain the cauallerie if need had required. The true number of thoſe that were ſlaine, were to the number of twoe thouſand &amp; two hundred, with their general the arle of <hi>Varas</hi> &amp; other perſonages of quality. There were 38. Enſignes, one cornet of horſe, &amp; fiue hundred pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; among them one of the earls of <hi>Manſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>field,</hi> twelue cheefe captaines, and many other offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers: many eſcaped, which had for their paſportes blowes on the heads with Coutelaces.</p>
            <p>His Ex. according to his natural clemencie and curteſie, had diſcharged the priſoners except ſome few which he would haue retained for the perfour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of the ranſomes of the reſt, had it not beene that ſome alledged, that the Cardinall commanded his people to breake the quarter: he retained them vntil he was reſolued of his intent, to the end to or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der things the better hereafter.</p>
            <p>Among the dead they did finde certaine reliques which did warrant men from the danger of warre, inchanted papers, coniurations of ſoules, and prai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ers which the preeſts doo vſe to ſel for money, ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the forme of praying to God, &amp; that which he doth require of man, that we may well ſay as did S. <hi>Barnard</hi> in his time, that the miniſters of Chriſt
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:2110:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:2110:6"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:2110:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> did ſeruice to Antichriſt, &amp; that they did ouerthrowe the foundation of the church, tranſporting the Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical dignities into an infamous gaine, and ſhewing themſelues to be repleniſhed with powre but not with iuſtice. It is here, where I woulde pray my maiſters the Catholikes (I mean the abu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed, not the abuſers, the which knowe beſt howe to open their eies and vnderſtandings) laying aſide al paſſion, to conſider if there be in the holy ſcriptures any thing which doth approch to theſe praiers. We do ſee in the Pſalmes of Dauid, that an infinite ſort of the ſeruants of God went to the warres, but we cannot finde any like vnto theſe inchantments and praiers in Latin, which are tranſlated at the ende of this diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>Behold the end of this iourney in ſteed of entring the Iſles as they aſſured themſelues: nay, ſoft and faire, ſuch cats are not to be caught without muf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fles, and not ſo eaſily ouercome without danger of wel drinking, as did thoſe which heretofore attemp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted to enter into the countrey of <hi>Yo<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e,</hi> and the Spa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>niards which were conducted by the late erle <hi>Char.</hi> of <hi>Manſfield</hi> into <hi>Bommelweert,</hi> in time likewiſe of froſt. Theſe <hi>Rodomon</hi> ſouldiors thought the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters to be no more difficult then the land, where for<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tune ſometime did ſmile on them: but the Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards (as cats which haue once wet their feete) are wiſer, then to vndertake ſuch thinges themſelues, but ſend others. The Ieſuites may preache their bellies ful before they can perſwade them. So like<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wiſe, the Cardinall is not like ſo eaſilie to conquer theſe Iſles as he thought: nay, he is rather buſied to prepare to defend himſelfe this ſummer, hauing ſomuch worke cut out, that of long time cannot bee
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:2110:7"/> made vp in thoſe places where hee thought to tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph.</p>
            <p>France as it is at this day, would not willinglie receiue the laſt lie, ſhe wil not indure you ſo to carie away her faire fethers as you did the tempeſt of the ciuill wars beeing not yet paſte: you deceiue your ſelues, if you thinke your ſtratagems of truce ſhall ſerue you to abuſe the French: no, they will throw away their rackets the game beeing ſo faire: they know your diſeaſe and where to begin with you, and wil ſhew themſelues not to be of ſo vile and baſtard courage, as you think them to be. So likwiſe thoſe of <hi>Orthois</hi> and <hi>Heinault,</hi> doe not looke for any other thing, then their own miſerable ouerthrow and vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter vndooing, for hauing ſerued the inſatiable ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Spaniard. There are in thoſe Prouin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces men of courage and not yet degenerated, whoe finding their owne greefe, doe know the remedie, &amp; that of neceſſitie they muſte purge the offenſiue hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor for to ſaue the whole bodie: they I ſaie, ſeeing my lords the Eſtates of the vnited prouinces, to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare vnto them ſo happily floriſhing in all ſortes of bleſſings that God may ſend to men, and to gouern themſelues with ſo many good pollicies and rules of diſcretion, cauſing ſo ſweet and happy a quietneſſe among the people, as in no countrey in the world ſoeuer, where menne in reaſon may find more occa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſion to content themſelues then there. A thing not to be maruailed at, ſith that we euidentlie know by ſo many euents paſt, that it is GOD which dooth guide and warrant them, as heeretofore he did his people againſt the Syrians, Egyptians, Aſſyrians, Medes and others: and it is not to be doubted but that he wil continue his fauour, ſeeing the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:2110:8"/> of their quarrel is his glory and the conſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of natural liberty, which ought to be as deare vnto vs as our liues; being void of all paſſions and reuenge in their conqueſt of townes, where ſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie it might ſeeme they ſhould haue vſed the ſame to ſerue for examples to others, in reſpect of ſome which were reuolted, which is an euident ſhewe of their benignity and true chriſtian gouernment, in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſteed of confuſion and crueltie with the which their enimies would charge them. And as I haue ſaide, their foundation is ſo ſtrong, as wee maye beleeue that the hammars which are prepared to breake this anuile, ſhal be battered, bruſed and broken, as they haue bin hitherto. Wee will reſt our ſelues then vpon the promiſes which our great God hath made, to conſerue thoſe which doe ſeeke his honour, and glorie, and extermine al thoſe who oppoſe them<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelues againſt the kingdome of his ſonne Ieſus.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="prayers">
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:2110:8"/>
            <div xml:lang="lat" type="version">
               <head>Quicunque hanc ſupraſcriptam orationem ſecu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> portauerit, nullum inimicum timeat, nec gladij, nec ſagitta, nec aliqua arma ſibi nocere poterunt: nec inſidiae diaboli, nec arma incantantium, nec veneno<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rum, nec immundus ſpiritus ſibi nocere poterunt, in omni te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pore, &amp; in omni loco ſaluus erit: <g ref="char:cross">✚</g>
                  <g ref="char:cross">✚</g>
                  <g ref="char:cross">✚</g>
               </head>
               <p>BArnaſa <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> leutias <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> buccella <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> buccella <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> agla <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> agla <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> tetra grammaton <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> adonay <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> Domine Deus magne &amp; mirabilis adiuua famulum tuum N: indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num ab omni periculo mortis, corporis, &amp; animae, &amp; ab omnibus inſidijs inimicorum, viſibilum &amp; inuiſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lium. <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> Decem ſunt nomina, quibus appellatur Deus, in quocunque <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> nomen Deus <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> Crux <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> ely <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> eloy <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> ela <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> adonay <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> corpus Chriſti cogi <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> ſabaot <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> nomina crux <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> haec proſint famulo Dei N. hoc eſt enim corpus meum, <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> vt diligat me, Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:lang="lat" type="version">
               <head>ORATIO.</head>
               <p>COniuro vos omnia arma cum quibus occiſi ſunt omnes ſancti Martyres, praecipio vobis per me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rita ſanctorum omnium, vt non habeatis poteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem ſcindendi carnem meam, nec ſanguinem me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um ſpargendi, nec offendendi me famulum Dei N. nec in aliquo laedendi. <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> Crux &amp; paſſio domini no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtri Ieſu Chriſti ſit in memoria &amp; in defenſione me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>a, pax &amp; benedictio domini ſit ſemper mecum: <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> ô ſagitta ſta per virtutem beatae Mariae Virginis, &amp; per caput ſancti Ioannis Baptiſtae, per Apoſtolos, Martyres, Confeſſores, Virgines &amp; Viduas: per An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelos &amp; Archangelos: ó ſagitta ſta per annunciati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Domini noſtri Ieſu Chriſti, <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> ô ſagitta ſta per coronam ſpineam; quae portata fuit in capite Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini noſtri Ieſu Chriſti. ó ſagitta ſta per captionem &amp; flagellationem Domini noſtri Ieſu Chriſti, <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> O ſagitta per clauos, qui perforauerunt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:2110:9"/> &amp; pedes Domini noſtri Ieſu Chriſti, ô ſagitta ſta per vulnera Domini noſtri Ieſu Chriſti, per reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectionem Domini noſtri Ieſu Chriſti: vt non poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis laedere me famulum Dei N. <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> In nomine Patris, &amp; Filij, &amp; ſpiritus ſancti, Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:lang="lat" type="version">
               <head>ORATIO.</head>
               <p>Obſecro te Domine fili Dei viui per ſanctam cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem tuam; vt dimittas peccata mea, <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> per ſanctam crucem tuam cuſtodi caput meum, per venerabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem crucem tuam cuſtodi pedes meos &amp; omnia me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bra mea, &amp; tribue mihi veniam &amp; vitam aeternam; <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> ſancte Deus ſanctifica me, fortis Deus fortifica me, immortalis Deus miſerere mei famuli tui N. quia peccata mea multa ſunt apud te, &amp; non ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus vocari ſeruus tuus propter iniquitates meas quae ſunt innumerabiles: propterea deprecor te, vt mittas in cor meum amorem caeleſtem. Qui viuis &amp; regnas deus per omnia ſecula ſeculorum, Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:lang="lat" type="version">
               <head>ALIA ORATIO.</head>
               <p>Abba Pater miſerere mei, <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> ô Fili, <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> ô ſancte ſpi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ritus mecum ſis: erue me ab omnibus aduerſariis meis, <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> coniuro te gladium per S. ſacerdotem vete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris teſtamenti, qui introduxit Mariam &amp; Dominum noſtrum Ieſum Chriſtum in templum dicentem: tuam ipſius animam doloris gladius pertranſibit, vt non poſsit laedere famulum Dei N. <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> Coniuro vos lapides per beatum Stephanum protomarty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem, quem Iudaei lapidauerunt, qui ſtatuit pro ſuis perſecutoribus exorare, dicens: N. Ne ſtatuas illis hoc peccatum, quia neſciunt quid faciunt, vt non poſsint laedere me famulum Dei N.] In nomine Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tris <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> &amp; Filij <g ref="char:cross">✚</g>, &amp; ſpiritus ſancti, <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:lang="eng" type="version">
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:2110:9"/>
               <head>Whoſoeuer ſhall carry about him this praier heere vnder written, let him not feare any enemy, neither can a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny weapon anoy him, neither darts nor other warlike in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument: neither the weapons of the inchanters, nor poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, neither can the wicked ſpirit annoy him: he ſhall be ſafe at all times, and in al places.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Arnaſa</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> 
                  <hi>leuitas</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> 
                  <hi>buccella</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> 
                  <hi>buccella</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> 
                  <hi>agla</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> 
                  <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gla</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> 
                  <hi>tetra grammaton</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> 
                  <hi>adonay</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:cross">✚</g>. Lord, great and admirable God, helpe thy vnworthie ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant, <hi>N.</hi> from all danger of death of the bodie and ſoule, &amp; from al the aſſaults of enemies, viſible and inuiſible <g ref="char:cross">✚</g>. There be tenne names with the which God is named, in whome <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> they name God <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> 
                  <hi>Crux</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> 
                  <hi>ely</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> 
                  <hi>eloy</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> 
                  <hi>ela</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> 
                  <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donai</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> 
                  <hi>Corpus Chriſti cogi</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> 
                  <hi>ſabaot</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> 
                  <hi>nomina Crux</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> the things are profitable to the ſeruant of God, <hi>N. hoc eſt enim corpus</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> 
                  <hi>meum</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> 
                  <hi>vt diligat me, Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I coniure you all weapons with the which all the ſaints haue bin martyred. I coniure you by the merits of al the ſaints, that you haue no power to cut my fleſh, nor ſhed my bloud, nor offend me the ſeruant of God, <hi>N.</hi> nor hurt me in any thing. The croſſe and paſſion of our Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſu Chriſt, bee in my mind and defence. The peace and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of our Lord be alwaies with me <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> O darte ſtaie thy ſelfe by the vertue of the bleſſed virgin Mary, and by the heade of S. Iohn Baptiſt, by the apoſtles, martyrs, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors, virgines and widowes: by the angels and arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>angels: O dart ſtay thy ſelfe by the annunciation of our L. Ieſus Chriſt, O dart ſtay thy ſelf by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> crown of thorns, which was ſet vpon the head of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, O dart ſtay thy ſelfe by the taking and beating of our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt: <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> O darte for the nailes which pearſed the hands and feete of our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt, O dart ſtaie for the wounds of our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt, by the reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt in ſuch ſort that thou haſt not the power to hurt me the ſeruant of God, <hi>N.</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> in the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:2110:10"/> name of the father, and of the ſonne, and the holie Ghoſt, Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:lang="eng" type="version">
               <head>A Prayer.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>I</hi> Beſeech thee by the holy croſſe, O Lord ſonne of the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing God, that thou forgiue me my ſinnes <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> keepe my hed by thy holie croſſe, kéepe my féete and all my mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers by thy venerable croſſe, and giue me remiſſion and eternall life. <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> bleſſed God ſanctifie me, mightie God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie me, immortall God haue compaſſion vppon me thy ſeruant <hi>N.</hi> becauſe that my ſinnes bee in great nomber before thee, and I am not worthie to be called thy ſeruant by reaſon of mine iniquities which are innumerable. Wherefore I beſeech thee that thou wilt ſende into my heart celeſtiall loue, who liueſt and raigneſt a God from age to age, Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:lang="eng" type="version">
               <head>Another Praier.</head>
               <p>ABba father, haue pittie on me <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> O ſonne <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> O holie ghoſt be with me, withdraw me from all mine aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries. <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> I coniure thee O blade by the holie prieſt of the old Teſtament, who brought Mary and our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt into the temple ſaying: the ſword ſhall go through thy ſoule with griefe, ſo that it ſhall not hurt the ſeruant of God <hi>N.</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> O ſtones I coniure you by the bleſſed Steuen the firſt martyr the which the Iewes ſtonied, who ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned that wee ſhould pray for our perſecutors, ſaying <hi>N.</hi> impute not that ſinne vnto them, for they know not what they do, ſo that they cannot offend me the ſeruant of God, <hi>N.</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:cross">✚</g>, in the name of the father, and of the ſonne, and of the holie Ghoſt <g ref="char:cross">✚</g>, Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:2110:10"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
